If you're really ready to start, I'm
inviting you to meet Aisha.
Aisha is a young unemployed artist and
the only adult in her family.
She comes from a very difficult
childhood.
She grew up with her
grandmother, and when she died, she
had to take care of her siblings. And she
has many siblings.
Six of them. Aisha has a long
difficult journey behind, really.
She comes from Kenya, and Kenya is a
country of, fifty-six
million people according to Statista.
Only a bit less of thirty of them is in
urban areas. The rest, which is almost
seventy percent, like Aisha, live in
rural areas and face several challenges.
And at this point, there is
something very, very strange for me when
I first started with this
project. But I think it's interesting
for the group.
In Kenya and all the other countries
I had the opportunity to investigate and
to talk with people from, data
in rural areas are much more
expensive than in the city. I don't know
how mobile companies, I mean
telephone, telephone companies are
structuring the prices there.
But, to have data in rural areas is
not so easy as to have data in the city
of the center. So Aisha has to travel
to get data when she needs to.
She does it. But what really
troubles her outside
this data problem are the
unstable basic infrastructure
and the utilities that they that she
doesn't always have regularly.
It can be water, it can be electricity.
And other challenges that she faces
as a woman is the violence against women,
which is higher in the rural areas, and
also discrimination against
minorities.
As Aisha says... Actually, as one of the
interviewees told me the more
outside of the center, the more difficult
life gets.
Despite data being expensive, Aisha
buys data packs and is one of the
twenty-two million internet users in
Kenya, and like most of them, she
accesses the internet through her mobile.
She doesn't have a computer.
She doesn't have a laptop. She's
lucky enough to own a smartphone, and,
despite she can still imagine
her life without internet, which
fifty-eight percent of her
people cannot.
It is very important, for her to
be able to go online every time she needs
to, so she makes sure that somehow
she finds data.
I don't know how the people there are
doing it.
I talked with a lot of people and a lot
of counselors, and especially, especially
counselors told me a young might not
have something to eat or might not be
able to, to go out. They don't have
money, but they find their way around
data. They find a way to go online. There
is some way of them.
Like most of her peers, she's
connected to WhatsApp and of course uses
Instagram, TikTok, and Facebook. She
uploads videos on YouTube and watches
movies on Gojara, which is, if I
understand correctly, something
equivalent with Netflix. Maybe
I'm wrong,
but it's something local in Kenya.
She and her friends use frequently,
ChatGPT, mostly to find new information
and to write in a formal tone of voice
when they need to. They know, they
have heard that AI can be dangerous,
however, they don't understand why. I
mean, they don't have a concrete idea,
okay, how can AI really be dangerous?
And Aisha for sure does not
realize, and this is probably important
for us, we need to address it from my
perspective, that the information
that she finds on ChatGPT, or to be
more consistent, information that ChatGPT
provides, might be a product of
hallucination. So this is something that,
that we need to be careful with because,
, it can be quite dangerous,
in our position.
Sorry. Yeah. Aisha is a typical
Kenyan Zoomer,
and as most of the Zoomers in Kenya,
she dreams of fame, fortune, and freedom.
She struggles with unemployment, worries
about the economic situation in her
country and the rising prices, and would
like to find a job that could offer her
money, vibes, and peace of mind. Not sure
who wouldn't, but this is also what Aisha
wants. Hoping to find success as a
dancer but realizing that life in Kenya
is hard for artists and she might never
be able to survive from her art only, if
Aisha could, she would happily leave
Kenya to live in a different country,
preferably in America, but would also
settle for Europe.
I told you already, her life has not been
easy.
She grew up with her grandma. When her
grandma died, she had to take care of her
six of her six brothers and sisters,
and she was only nineteen at the time.
And as you can imagine, being at that age
and guardian of six without any good
education or perspective for the future
was challenging, overwhelming, and
frightening. She and her siblings
struggled a lot, and she knew she was the
one who should do something about it. She
was the only adult.
She was trying to figure things out,
and at some point, somehow she
became aware of Swahili Pot Hub
Foundation.
She found Swahili, Swahili Pot on
her Facebook timeline.
Visiting their Facebook page, she
realized...
You can see some ads that Swahili Pot
has on Facebook.
She realized that Swahili Pot
provides, a lot of opportunities for
young people like her in Mombasa, and,
it has helped youths from very
different backgrounds.So she had nothing
to lose.
Maybe they could help her. She was,
anyway, very, in a very difficult
position. Visiting their website
she read that Swahili Pot
empowers youth to reach their full
potential.
This is their main mission.
And they have four key programs that
focus on different challenges. For
example, sustainable
employment, heritage tourism as a job
opportunity, women empowerment to attend
tech programs, and, a campus
ambassador program where they try to,
talk with young people, at
colleges and help them find,
jobs. Like a
counselor,
at Swahili Pot said, in
one of our own conversation,
Swahili Pot tries to take youth from
the streets and keep them occupied
until they can make something of
themselves with their lives.
And they're trying to protect their,
their youth, Kenyan youth to not
use drugs, to not sell, to not sell
drugs, to find other, type of
enjoyment and other opportunities of
gaining money.
And, as you can see on the pictures,
they have very different and some very,
very creative approaches to keep
the youth together and allow them
express themselves in a productive, not
self-harming way until they can
advance themselves and their careers.
Aisha, when,
when she found Swahili
Pot, was very, very, very, very
lucky, that, when she went
there, she stamped upon a very sweet,
very empathetic, very supportive person.
And I, I want to stress at this point
that the most counselors I talked with,
from anywhere, were very,
very, very empathetic, very supportive,
ready to listen, ready to share, and they
were really caring about the people
that they were counseling.
Especially in Kenya, they were really,
feeling their jobs.
I mean, I cannot express it enough,
but they were really there for
the people that they were
supporting.
And Aisha was lucky to find one
of them.
This person was Amina. Amina Kibet.
Amina is a program manager, mentor
coordinator, who also acts as the
first point of contact for youth coming
to the organization. Remember that in
these organizations, usually one person
doesn't have one job. Uh, they do
different things, mix and match.
I mean, they are NGOs mostly, from my
understanding.
And they need, to fill
many gaps and wear many hats.
So Amina is one of them, is a program
manager, mentor coordinator, and the
first point of contact. Is
forty-three years old, is an accomplished
leader and she strives to
provide the best she can really, the
best to her mentees. To do that, her
number one priority is to
provide tailored mentoring and support to
every single person coming to Swahili
Pot. And, as you can see, the second
one is to expand the reach of the
organization. So she wants to help as
many people as possible, as many
young people as possible. And Aisha was
very lucky,
when she first approached Swahili
Pot, Amina was the one she met, and Amina
was the one she would guide her through
the self-discovery process.
This is what that's, there,
there is a process at Swahili Pot that
they call self-discovery. Is when,
counselors try to come to the
young people. As Yasin said before,
young people don't really know
themselves. They don't know their skills.
They don't know their strengths.
most importantly, and for me, quite
mind-blowing, during the research,
they, they don't know their interests.
They don't know what they like, what they
don't like. And, so these
counsellors try to be there and,
guide them through processes and,
have them interact
with their peers, try out different
things, and find themselves somehow.
And at Swahili Pot, they call this
process the self-discovery process.
During this process, Amina with
her empathy, non-judgmental approach,
helped Aisa realize what her life is and
what it could be, where she was and where
she wanted to go. And then she
helped her also define goals and
priorities and make a plan to get there.
So,
in other words, as a Kenyan mentor at
Swahili Pot, would say Amina was the first
person of contact for Aisa and the one
supporting her throughout her
self-discovery journey to find...
Sorry,
I mixed the slides a bit.
Yeah, sorry for that. As a young
person living in poverty, taking
care of, of six minors, what Aisa
prioritized in this journey was her
ability to take care of herself and
her family.
In other words, her financial
stability, professional growth, and,
recognition was number one, number two, and three.
And despite having an enormous
amount of passion for her art, she loves
dancing. And there are many artists
in Kenya.
This is why this is important. She,
she... Amina helped her realize that
her low income, her financial instability
would not change unless she makes some
changes, maybe some sacrifices, and find
some stable source of income for herself.
She shouldn't leave dance
behind, but it is a realization that,
Kenya is not a country where artists can
flourish, at least not at the moment.
So probably she would need more,
things to do some more things in order
to be able to survive. Through
several discussions and explorations
with Anima and the other
mentors, and her peers at Swahili Pod,
somehow Aisha came across a second
organization in Kenya. Which is really,
common as far as I went
through the research that
people are part of more than one
organizations.
that young people get help from as
many organizations as they can,
and maybe some of them,
overlap with one another.
So, Aisha, in this case came
across a second organization in Kenya,
which is eMobilis. It's a mobile
technology institute,
and Aisha heard about eMobilis in one of
her mentoring classes at Swahili Pod, and
then she found their ads on Instagram,
and their messages resonated with her.
So one of the messages, for example,
the only thing standing between her and
her goal was a story she kept telling
herself, and she would like to
change that. She wanted to
change the storyline.
So she decided to give them a try,
reach out to them, and before doing
that, she visited their website, and
there she discovered that eMobilis has
different programs to connect youths to
digital opportunities.
And their programs are all related to
tech, education, and include, a mobile
and web development program, digital
literacy initiatives, and women in tech
interventions. Women in tech
interventions are important, because,
women in Kenya, also in India, I
don't know about South Africa,
are quite afraid that they will not
make it in STEM professions, that
they, they are not capable enough.
They don't feel comfortable talking
about their achievements. They feel that,
their men counterparts are more
capable. And this is something that,
these organizations, most of them,
are trying to overcome. So,
this is something that they try
to provide to young women. eMobilis' most prominent
intervention is the Ajira program.
Ajira program is a cooperation of
eMobilis with the
government, and from this program
came all the people that I talked to, so
I'm not so well equipped to answer
questions from the other programs. But Ajira program is a cooperation with
the government designed to train, mentor,
and connect young people with digital
opportunities. They facilitate
placement throughout online
freelance platforms, you might have heard
Upwork, for example, and provide
ongoing support and training to
ensure job readiness for their
participants. So someone might go to
the Ajira program without having any
idea. They might know nothing about,
about tech, and they take him from,
from the hand, and they walk
them through the program.
They choose an occupation. It
could be web development.
It could be web design. It could be
transcription.
I mean, it doesn't always have to be
really techy.
It can be something more simple,
but there are occupations that,
have to happen,digitally on a
computer.
People don't own the computers.
The Ajira program provides the
computers at their stations, so there
is a limitation on how many people can
participate because they don't have
hundreds of computers.
But the people who participate go
through the training.
Then they go through some kind of
mentoring, where they help them,
build up their skills, their
self-presentation skills, their soft
skills, how they should communicate,
how they should write offers, things like
that. And then at the end, they help
them with creating their online profiles
on Upwork, for example. They have other
platforms as well, which are more local,
but they also are on Upwork. And
they create their profiles.
They highlight the skills that are
more marketable or their skills that they
are more strong at. From my
experience with a participant,
they focus more on the
marketable part rather than being
good because at the beginning the
trainers help them complete the task so
that they can get some good
recommendations, some good ratings
from their clients. And then some,
at some point, they become more
independent. Everything is free. The
person who is participating doesn't pay a
thing. It's supported by the
government, and people in Kenya tend to
prefer it versus other programs because,
as a participant told me
being from the government is more
trustworthy.
There are many scams. I don't
know.
This is what I've been told. And
having this recommended
by the government, it is something that
helps build
trust around the program. And so,
Aisha went there,
and considering the government,
governmental support that I told you
about, she decided to join. Being
new in tech, she
struggled a lot. I mean, she was not new.
She, she had no idea about tech, so it's
a new field, a new world for her.
She's a dancer.
She might be good at math when she
was at high school, but at the moment,
she struggles a lot to decide which
trainings she should go through.
She should go through web development.
She should go through web design.
And should she make transcriptions?
What should she do at this Ajira
program? She wasn't sure, so she
calls and asks if she
could arrange an info session with one of
the trainers or one of the mentors, with
someone who could help her. And when
she called, she found James.
James is a tech expert, PR manager,
and trainer at eMobilis
and especially in the Ajira
program.
He's a seasoned professional, a very
attentive-to-detail person, and has
exceptional organizational skills and
deep knowledge in his domain.
He's always happy to share his expertise
with the students.
He's very dedicated to his work, and
very, very supportive to the youth
he mentors. When Aisha reached out,
to his organization, he immediately
proposed to meet, and he thought,
"Okay, let's meet her.
Let's see, who this person is. Let's
ask some questions.
Let's discuss and see what she can do,
what she could do, what she would like to
do. And he immediately, uh
she immediately accepted and decided
that they will meet to see what
training would be the best opportunity
for her.
He was very excited to meet her
and, as his
main motivation is to create impact for
his community, to have impact
in Kenya... he was, "Why not?
Let's do that."
And while, Aisha is meeting
with
James, let's give them some space to
talk.
Let us travel a bit further and
meet someone else.
Meet Tumelo. Tumelo is 29 years old.
He doesn't live in Kenya.
He lives in Cape Town. He lives with
his mother and his sister and
despite being an N4-certified mechanic,
- from my understanding this is a
technical education that they complete
in South Africa - he's
the only one in his family without a job,
and this is very disappointing, very
humiliating. So his mother has a job, his
sister has a job, but he has no job.
He tried several times, so many times, to
start his own business, but he's not good
with business management. He's not good
with finances.
He failed. He didn't have support. He
didn't know whom to talk to.
And now he does not see his
worth, and he feels he will
never, never, never make it. And he's
young, but not so young anymore.
He's 29, so he, he really, really feels
the pressure that he needs to do
something, but he believes that he will
not be able to do anything with his life.
Tumelo's very disappointed. Very,
very disappointed.
He would like to be independent, have
financial stability.
He would like to run his own business
as a mechanic or find a job
that could help him at
least earn his own money and become
independent, leave his home, and
live on
his own. As said, he has lost any
hope.
He strives for recognition. He
needs to feel it.
He really needs to feel like he's
achieving something to be able at
least to contribute to his household, not
only take money from
his mother or his sister.
But he cannot find anything at the
moment.
He lacks self-awareness, has a very low
self-esteem, and, the truth is that,
some years ago, when he was achieving
this certification, Tumelo was very
optimistic. He was a young person. He
thought he would find a job.
He would be able to become independent
very soon.
He would conquer the world. I mean, he
was young.
But then reality hit him. He lives in
South Africa,
and in South Africa, youth
unemployment has reached 50,5%
in 2023. So Tumelo is not alone. Of
course he's not alone.
There are other people like him.
And he's one of the young people who live
in South Africa without a job, but he's
disappointed.
He knew he would probably have some
struggles, not struggles, some
challenges to find a job because he knew
that, that there was this unemployment in
South Africa, but he was... As said, he
was optimistic because he had a paper.
He had something. Still, it didn't work
out.
To make sure that he would be
more successful or to try to be more
successful, trying to find a job,
Tumelo joined, Harambee, the
Youth Employment Accelerator, and
there he took part in the different work
readiness workshops Harambee
offered.
Actually, pre-COVID, Harambee conducted
daily these workshops, and they did it at
their local offices but also in remote
areas around the communities.
The workshops should prepare young folks
to get for potential jobs.
See, many young people in South Africa,
not Tumelo in that case, but there are
people like that, grow up with none
of their parents working.
So they're born in households where no
one is working, and these are people
who do not know how it looks like to wake
up and go to, to work.
They don't know that, you have to be,
at your job at a specific time.
And they live in poverty. They,
they do not realize what they would
need to do to change their lives.
Maybe they succeed, maybe not
because, as said, in South Africa, the
situation is not so simple. If
you go to the...
to your job on time doesn't guarantee
that you will have a job.
But there are people who do not know
what they need to do to have this job.
So, in the work readiness workshops,
Harambee did a great job trying
simulating the work conditions and
teach these people how they should behave
in a professional setting. And it was
very, mind-blowing for me, and I
heard it last week because South Africa
research is quite ongoing,
that for example, for jobs that
you need to stand for hours, if it's,
something, that, that you need to
stand, they had, in this work...
in these workshops they had the people
standing.
And if there is a job that you need
to wear any kind of equipment,
they had these
people being there with the
equipment wearing the equipment
for hours so that they get used to it.
Because for Harambee at this
point was, was important that the people
understand what the job is about, but
also that they understand the conditions,
they get used to the conditions. And when
they start on the job, they don't...
they don't leave because of the
conditions.
So, this was very interesting.
Anyway, Tumelo attended a couple of the
workshops himself. Still he had no
success getting a job, and in the
meantime, also Harambee switched
their offerings, because, when
COVID with the lockdown hit South Africa,
of course Harambee could not make the,
the workshops anymore. So, they
transitioned from an offline, on-site
here and now world, where they
were able to
communicate, to come in touch with the
people.
They transitioned to the
digital world.
And started instead of
delivering co- work readiness workshops
on site to offer, work
readiness content, which is quite
different, through their mobi,
their data-free mobile site instead.
Parenthesis here, the problem
with the data is also
in South Africa. So also in South Africa,
in rural areas, the data...
the data is more expensive. In the city are,
are not so expensive, but still young
people without jobs, struggle to find
the data that they need to go
online. So there is this offering
from some organizations,
in South Africa, that allow
people to visit their websites without
the usage of data. And from a
conversation I had with the
social media manager at Harambee, she
told me that also Facebook, for
example, has this opportunity, where
you can go online on Facebook,
and you can read the text without using
data, but you cannot see the pictures.
So, when they are
doing this social media ads
or something, she always has to have the
picture, but also have a description of
the picture, so that people who
are on the data-free version of Facebook,
they can read what's going on with
the picture.
And to move forward, Harambee offers
a wide range of services on their mobi.
It's data-free, I said before, which is
profile creation, entrepreneurial
opportunities, because they try to,
find,
ways that young people,
become somehow independent, earn their
own money. And being a micro
entrepreneur or being an entrepreneur is,
sometimes quite more easy to do than
finding an employer who would hire you.
Employment opportunities, upskilling
opportunities if needed, and they also
have this interviewing and job searching
tips, hustling tips, how you could earn
some money on the side. And as Christian,
said in the beginning, and
I want to stress it, it's not that they
try to, to get away from the law.
It's not that the young people,
or the older people who do
something in the market
that is not
100% seen, are trying to get away
with something.
But they need to survive.
And Harambee wants to help them,
survive and at the same time upskill
themselves, find jobs that are
seen and registered.
And to move a bit forward
and return to our storyline
Tumelo, like
most mobi users become usually aware
of the site either through the different
campaigns Harambee has on
the streets, they have many campaigns on
the streets or via social media.
And this is also where Tumelo
realized that he could use Harambee
platform, it might...
it might could help him, and he
decided to register.
Here you can see the..., I don't
know how much time we have, to be
honest, so I don't know if you want to go
through the flow that he went through to
register somewhere later. More
or
less he, when someone has
to register on the Harambee,
mobi site, they need to visit the
platform mostly from the
mobile phone. So 99% of the users come
from mobile,
and they provide the ID number or the
passport number and their personal
details. As Joss, Joss is the
Head of Design at Harambee, told me,
they have this process with ID
number to, first of all,
to validate the data that they
receive.
Second of all, it was through user
testings that they have done:
It seemed more secure for users to
provide their ID number to Harambee
rather than connect Harambee with their
social media profiles.
They didn't trust the social
media companies to log in to
the Harambee site. And they provide
their zip code
and address details, which is
important because they allow Harambee to,
help them find a job in their area.
This is part of their value
proposition, that they will help them
find a job in their area.
And this is important because it's really
difficult for young people to travel to
find a job in a different area than their
own.
They might need to take a taxi,
and the taxi is really expensive.
And as it's quite difficult to be on
time... For some reason, they
will not never be on time for
their job, so...
And they will not keep the job long-term.
So it's important to find a job, at least
the first job, in their area. This is
what Harambee
promises. And browsing around
the platform,
he couldn't find any opportunity. So
now he's
quite, disappointed, and he does
not visit Seyath Mobi,
so frequently. He's still hoping to
find a job, of
course, but, maybe if he could
present himself better on paper, or if
he could talk about his strengths and
weaknesses with confidence, he would be
able to get the job that he needs and,
break out of this disappointing
circle. If he were aware about his
skills, had his skills on a paper,
had a way to communicate the skills,
he might had a better chance,
At this point, we can
think of ways to help Tumelo.
But while we're thinking, let's,
leave him out with his other unemployed
friends, talking about life and how
hard South Africa can be for the youth.
And let's move forward to have a
look at someone else.
This someone else is someone who uses
Harambee platform very frequently and
who's overly committed to change her
fate.
She did it already once anyway, so,
she believes, and why not?
She could do it again. So this is Kabo.
Kabo is a minimum wage worker, but for
Kabo, being that minimum wage worker is
a big success.
This is important to remember. It's
successful.
To get this one minimum wage job, she
had to move from her hometown, and this
is the promise of Harambee comes in,
to another place, Pretoria.
So, it was impossible to find a
job in her hometown, any
job, and she had to move to get a minimum
wage job.
So, to move there and to get
this one minimum wage job, her mother had
to borrow money for her travel. So,
her mother borrowed money to allow her
daughter travel and find a job.
Now she's in Pretoria, with a
job, and she lives with her cousin. Her
cousin is the one also who helped her
find a job at the first place. She
cannot stay with her cousin forever.
She knows that. So she's trying to find
another job, a better paying job that,
would allow her to become
independent, grow professionally,
and skill herself up. To achieve
that, she needs empowerment.
She really needs empowerment. She feels
stuck, overwhelmed, and under pressure.
And despite... She's very grateful,
don't take it wrong.
She's very grateful for her job and is
quite proud of herself for making it to
Pretoria. I mean, it's an achievement.
But she also feels
stuck, overwhelming... She's...
her working conditions are bad.
She has to do a lot of overtime, and
despite being paid for it, I mean, we
don't do it always to be paid for it,
she misses sleep, and she misses out of
job activities. So, she needs to
sleep.
She needs to somehow have a more
normal life.
She's not sure what she should do next.
She's very confused because she has
a job and tries to find
opportunities and tries to see
what's out there for her. And therefore,
she visits Mobi every single day.
She looks for personalized
recommendations, sends applications, and
searches for jobs and content that
could be helpful for her growth.
So, she needs to, she needs to grow.
Kabo tries to keep her CV on the
platform updated. However, she did not
have the time to complete any of the
assignments Harambee offers for boosting
her CV.
I think this is something, also
Christian and the Oxford team, or Yacine,
mentioned before, that
another team is working on.
She didn't have the time to do it
because she works all the time.
Still, as you see, to find a
better paying job and move out of her
cousin's place, Kabo tries anything she
can think of.
Like, for example, Harambee's AI chatbot,
Coach Me.
Harambee has an AI chatbot,
which is called Coach Me, that offers
goal-setting support and personalized
advice through a conversational
experience with an AI agent on WhatsApp
environment.
So, it's not like... From my
understanding from the conversation with
the people at Harambee, this is quite
different from what we are trying to
build because, they focus on
interview preparation and how
they can improve their
performance,
during the application process. So I
think, Tabiya is a bit earlier in the
process. To be honest, it was a surprise
for me to, to discover this tool, so I'm
still trying to analyze the data that I
collected about this tool.
But I just wanted to let you know
that Harambee has a chatbot,
Coach Me, their users are using it,
and from my understanding, they were
really happy when it got out and,
when it went out.
And, as the people that I talked
from Harambee told me, they...
it was a big success when they first
launched.
But I don't really have more information
than that.
And at this point, before we
move forward, I'd like to highlight that
everything that was presented, the key
insights that follow, and everything
that we will discuss in this session are
collected within a timeline of two
months. So, there are many things
missing.
There are still findings getting
processed, and there are still findings
getting synthesized. There are... we,
still have many unknowns.
Apostolos told it already. And we'll
need to investigate further, especially
for South Africa, where our research,
as I told you from my part, I mean,
Oxford has great research, on the
taxonomy, on the labor market, but on the
user side, the research that we have
from South Africa on the people side of,
of our people is quite superficial from
my perspective.
And we did not have a chance to
talk to the end users.
This, this is also something that I'm
missing.
The personas that were presented Tumelo
and Cabo were based on
Harambee's personas. So, we don't
really know how they would...
we didn't have the... I didn't
have the opportunity to talk to them to
see, okay, what are they doing with Gen
AI?
What are they doing with
online tools?
What, what... How do they approach their
lives?
So it's everything that Harambee had
there, and also the, the knowledge of
Harambee. So it's quite distant. And
especially I didn't have a chance to
talk with anyone from Harambee side about
micro-entrepreneurs, who from what I
hear are very important for Tabiya and
Harambee, but also, the big unknown
user group for me personally. As
none has provide any concrete insights
about these people, their worlds, who are
they?
What are they doing? So, this is
something that I want to stress out.
That we have unknowns. Still, I hope
and I believe that we have many knowns
that we could work with and move
forward.